Guide to the Joseph North and Helen Oken North Family Papers TAM.605
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
North (Joseph and Helen Oken) Family Papers
1913-1990
1930-1970
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
North, Joseph
North, Helen Oken
TAM.605
13.25 Linear Feet in 10 record cartons, 2 oversize flat boxes, 2 shoe boxes, and 1 manuscript box
The North (Joseph and Helen Oken) Family Papers (dated 1913-1990) include three generations of family correspondence and memorabilia spanning from the early 20th century to the 1990s. The bulk of the collection relates to Joseph and Helen North, but a significant portion also relates to Helen’s family and includes the papers of her father and mother Morris and Jennie Oken, and her sisters Lydia Oken Mates and Mary Oken Wilson. The collection is largely comprised of correspondence, which documents the North and Oken families’ involvement in the Communist Party, socialist activism, labor organizing, the Spanish Civil War, and family life. This collection also contains a significant amount of materials related to Joseph North's career as a journalist for the communist publications New Masses and the Daily Worker.
Scope and Content Note
The North (Joseph and Helen Oken) Family Papers (dated 1913-1990) include three generations of family correspondence spanning from the early 20th century to the 1990s. The bulk of the collection relates to Joseph and Helen North, but a significant portion also relates to Helen’s family and includes correspondence of her father and mother Morris and Jennie Oken, and her sisters Lydia Oken Mates and Mary Oken Wilson. The collection largely consists of correspondence written between the 1930s and 1970s, and also includes family photographs, notes, and memorabilia.
Joseph and Helen North's papers document several major themes in their lives including their careers, political activism, economic struggles, and children. A small amount of correspondence relates to their time in Spain during the Spanish Civil War where Joseph worked as a foreign correspondent for the communist publication the New Masses and Helen worked in the medical service. Their papers also include materials related to Joseph's work as a journalist, both before and after Spain. Other materials inlcude correspondence from friends and family and materials related to their three children.
Correspondence between Helen and her sisters is exceptionally rich and provides an intimate look into their personal lives touching on a wide array of topics including their jobs, political beliefs, relationships, family planning and contraception, children, and care of their aging parents. They provide a unique view of how Communist Party members balanced their political activism and family obligation, and the ways in which family influenced political belief.
The papers of Morris and Jennie Oken also make up a small portion of this collection. Morris Oken was active in a number of labor and socialist organization in New York City, and his papers contain a large amount of material related to communism and political activism. The collection also contains a significant amount of materials related to Helen's sister Lydia and her husband Dave Mates. Lydia Oken Mates worked for many years as a Communist Party organizer in Detroit and Dave Mates was a Veteran of the Abraham Lincoln Brigades who was also involved in Communist Party activism throughout his life.
Other materials contained in this collection include clippings, flyers, and ephemera, a small number of negatives, and two artifacts: a hat taken from a Moroccan soldier who died in Spain, and a tsarist-era naval uniform cap from Russia.
Materials added to the collection in 2017 largely relate to Joseph North’s writings and his work as a correspondent during the Spanish Civil War. They include press releases from the Spanish Republican Army’s Ministry of National Defense as well as several reports and first-hand accounts from volunteers in the International Brigades. Also included among these materials is unpublished novel titled, I Come from America as well a folder of obituaries and articles paying tribute to Joseph North following his death in 1976.
Many of the correspondents in this collection are addressed by a variety of names throughout their correspondence. Helen and her family often address each other by their Russian names or variations of those names. In much of her correspondence Helen is often addressed as Vezl, Vezlenka, Honushinka, Annunshinka, or Anne. Joseph North, who was born Jacob Soifer, is also addressed as Jacob or Jake on many occasions, and in several instances his letters are addressed to Jacob Sofier. Helen’s sister Lydia is often addressed as Lidushka, Liducinka, or Lilian, her sister Mary is addressed as Manya or Maninka; her father Morris is frequently referred to as Mitaya, and her mother Jennie, whose name is often spelled Jenny, is often referred to as Jenja.
Arrangement
This collection has been divided into five series by creator or by form. Correspondence in the first three series is arranged chronologically by recipient while other materials contained in these series have been grouped by creator. Series I has been further divided in four subseries. The first three subseries contain correspondence, which is arranged chronologically by recipient, while the fourth subseries contains memorabilia is arranged chronologically and by form. The last two series of the collection contain photographs and artifacts. Photographs have been grouped by creator.
Historical/Biographical Note
Joseph North was born Jacob Soifer in Ukraine to Jessie Soifer and Balia Yasnitz in in 1904. The family immigrated to the United States when he was 9 months old and settled in Pennsylvania. Joseph North began working in a Pennsylvania textile mill at the age of 12, and later worked summers in the ship yards of his hometown. Joseph graduated with a B.A. from the University of Pennsylvania and worked for several years after his graduation as a reporter for a variety of Pennsylvania newspapers. In 1935 he was one of the founders of the weekly New Masses and served as its editor for 15 years. Joseph North also served as a communist party organizer and a correspondent for the Daily Worker. Through his work as a journalist he reported on a number of major events including labor strikes of the 1930s, the Spanish Civil War, and World War II.
Helen Oken North was born in the Bronx, New York in 1912 to Russian immigrants Morris and Jennie Oken. Helen Oken was the youngest of five siblings, two sisters and two brothers. Her older brother Semyon was her mother’s son from a previous marriage who eventually left to live with his father, and her brother Yaksha, born in 1906, died when he was only year old after contracting an illness during the family’s passage to the United States. Helen and her two older sisters Mary and Lydia were born in New York and maintained close ties throughout their lives. The Oken family was highly involved in labor and socialist organizations. Helen's father Morris Oken was a textile worker and was active in the Workmen's Circle as well as other labor organizations. Helen was also involved in union activity and worked a labor organizer as a teenager. She later worked as a Communist party organizer in Pennsylvania in the 1930s. Helen’s sisters Lydia was also highly involved in political activism and worked as a Communist Party organizer in Detroit and Chicago. She married Abraham Lincoln Brigade volunteer Dave Mates in 1930.
Helen Oken married Joseph North in 1931. Joseph worked as a correspondent for the New Masses in Spain during the Spanish Civil War. Helen accompanied him to Spain and worked in the medical service during those years. Helen and Joseph later settled in Manhattan and had three children Daniel, Susan, and Nora. Helen continued to be involved in Communist Party activism. She also assumed the role of breadwinner on many occasions, as Joseph’s work as a journalist did not provide enough to support a family and often required him to travel abroad. Helen and Joseph were married for 26 year, but eventually divorced in 1957. Helen married Communist Party of the United States leader Gil Green in 1970. Joseph North also remarried, marrying Daily World journalist and editor Augusta Strong in 1963. Joseph's wife Augusta died in early 1976 and Joseph died in December of that same year. Helen North died in 1990.
Related Archival Materials
Collections related to the Joseph and Helen Oken North Papers include the Joseph North Spanish Civil War Artifacts (ALBA 294), David Mates Papers (ALBA 279), and Series VIII: Publication, Subseries A: People's Weekly World Administrative Records, 1919-2001 in the Communist Party of the United States Papers (TAM 132), which contains files related to Joseph North's work with the Daily Worker.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Nora North sent a gift of 12 boxes of family papers and correspondence in 2012. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 2012.013 and 2012.090. An additional donation of 2 boxes of materials was made in 2013. The accession number associated with this gift is 2013.046. In 2016, Nora North sent an additional box of Joseph North's papers. The accesison number associated with this gift is 2017.007.
Appraisal
Several published materials have been removed from this collection including copies of the Daily Worker and Daily World, magazines, and new paper clippings. Other materials of limited research value which consisted of receipts, empty envelopes, locks of hair were also removed from the collection.
Journalism, Communist -- United States.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Photographs; Correspondence; Scrapbooks.; Communists -- United States.; Women communists -- United States.; Jewish communists -- United States.; North, Joseph; North, Helen Oken; Oken, Morris, 1883-1953; Oken, Jennie, 1882-1959; Mates, David; Mates, Lydia Oken
- Series I: Joseph and Helen Oken North Papers, 1920-1990; 8 boxes
  Scope and Content Note
  This series primarily consists of incoming correspondence to Joseph and Helen North from the late 1920s to the 1970s. Correspondence contained in this collection consists of letters from family and friends to Joseph and Helen North. This series also includes materials such as datebooks, account ledgers, handwritten notes, receipts, memorabilia, diplomas, clippings, and drawings.
  - Subseries I.A: Helen Oken North Correspondence
    This sub-series contains incoming correspondence written to Helen North between the 1920s and 1970s. The majority of correspondence written to Helen comes from her sisters, parents, and her husband Joseph North. These letters discuss work, political activism, and family life. A large portion of these letters are in roughly chronological order and are from a wide array of correspondents. Other incoming letters have been grouped by subject or by sender.
    - Helen Oken North: Incoming Correspondence, 1928-1938; 51 folders (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
    - Helen Oken North: Incoming Correspondence, 1937-1949; 1 box (Box 2, Folder 1-15)
    - Helen Oken North: Incoming Correspondence, 1947-1954; 1 box (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
    - Helen Oken North: Incoming Correspondence, 1952-1966; 1 audiocassettes (Box 4, Folder 1-11)
    - Helen Oken North: Incoming Family Correspondence from Mary O. Wilson, 1943-1946; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Helen Oken North: Incoming Correspondence from Mary O. Wilson, 1930s, 1958-1965; 3 folders (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
    - Helen Oken North: Incoming Family Correspondence from Lydia O. Mates, 1936-1958; 2 folders (Box 4, Folder 16-17)
    - Helen Oken North: Incoming Correspondence from Lydia Mates, 1958-1965; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Helen Oken North: Correspondence from Linda Weber, 1943-1949; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Helen Oken North: Incoming Correspondence-Los Angeles 1949, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Helen and Nora North: Los Angeles 1949, 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Helen Oken North: Outgoing Correspondence (drafts), 1930s, 1940s, 1950s; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Subseries I.B: Joseph North Correspondence
    This sub-series contains correspondence related to Joseph North. A large portion this section consists of incoming letters to Joseph North which have been arranged in chronological order. This sub-series also contains letters related to the Spanish Civil War, which have been incorporated into this collection from the Joseph North Spanish Civil War Artifacts, ALBA 294. Many of the letters contained in these folders were written by Joseph North and addressed to his wife Helen.
    - Joseph North: Incoming Correspondence, 1930-1959; 8 folders (Box 5, Folder 6-18)
    - Joseph North Letter to "Comrade Gurewitsch", undated; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Joseph North: Correspondence, undated; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Joseph North: Incoming Correspondence - Spanish Civil War, 1936-1938; 2006.003; 2 folders (Box 5, Folder 21-22)
    - Joseph North: Spanish Civil War Correspondence and Clippings, 1936-1938; 2006.003; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Jim Lardner to Joseph North, undated; 2000.003; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Joseph North: Correspondence in Spain, 1937-1939; 2 folders (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Joseph North: Incoming Correspondence: Sympathy Regarding Death of Augusta North, 1976; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Joseph North and Nora North: Correspondence, 1976; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence and Materials related to Death of Joseph North, 1976-1977; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Joseph North: Correspondence and Materials related to I.O.S. speech in Helsinki, 1976; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Joseph North: Notes and Ephemera, 1976; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Jacob Sofier: Correspondence, 1932; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Subseries I.C: Joseph and Helen Oken North Correspondence
    This sub-series contains correspondence addressed to both Helen and Joseph North from their friends and family. A significant amount of materials contained within this sub-series also relate to Helen and Joseph's children Daniel, Susan, and Nora North. Many of these letters are addressed to the North children, either individually or collectively, while other letters contained in this section relate to the North children but have been addressed to their mother Helen. There is also a small amount of undated notes and correspondence between Joseph and Helen North.
    - Joseph and Helen Oken North: Incoming Correspondence, 1930-1959; 7 folders (Box 6, Folder 9-15)
    - Joseph and Helen Oken North: Correspondence from Anna Sokolow, undated; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Joseph and Helen Oken North: Correspondence from Friends, 1938-1948; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Notes between Joseph and Helen North, undated; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Assorted Correspondence between Helen and Joseph North, 1938-1950; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1930s and 1940s; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Joseph and Helen North: Correspondence, 1930s-1950s; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Notes Helen and Joseph North, 1930s; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - North Children: Notes and Correspondence, 1935-1959; 5 folders (Box 7, Folder 8-12)
    - Correspondence regarding Daniel North, 1939-1952; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Daniel North letters to Helen North-Summer Roadtrip, 1948; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Notes and Correspondence related to Susan North, 1936-1957; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Notes and Correspondence related to Nora North, 1942-1973; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Subseries I.D: Joseph and Helen Oken North Family Records and Memorabilia
    This sub-series contains a variety of memorabilia related to Joseph and Helen North. Materials related to Joseph and Helen include membership cards, memorabilia, pamphlets, drawings, and ephemera. Several materials contained in this section related to their children including homework, drawings, other memorabilia related to schooling and childhood. There are also several documents related to Joseph and Helen North's financial struggles including documents related to a rent dispute in 1945 and an Internal Revenue Service audit between 1948-1950. Also contained in this sub-series are a number of personal items such as account books, diplomas, date books, wallets and billfolds, notebooks, and autograph books.
    - Joseph and Helen Oken North: Assorted Notes and Drafts, 1930s and 1940s; 2 folders (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
    - Drawings and Sketches, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Joseph and Helen Oken North: Assorted Clippings and Ephemera, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Joseph and Helen Oken North: IRS Audit, 1948-1950; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Joseph North: I Come From America (unpublished manuscript), undated (Box 15, Folder 1-4)
    - Joseph North: Obituaries and Death Announcements, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Joseph North Rent Dispute, Feb. 1945; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Joseph North: Spanish Civil War Reports and National Defense Press Releases, 1937-1938 (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
    - Paris Memorabilia, 1938; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Children's Drawings and Homework, 1948-1951; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Daniel North Homework, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Daniel North Travel Diary, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Susan North Diploma and Graduation Programs, 1953, 1957; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Nora North Notes and Ephemera, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Materials Related to Helen Oken North Memorial, 1912-1990; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Anna Sokolow Posters and Programs, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - "The Young Pioneers of America - Course for Pioneers of Leadership", Jul. 23, 1938; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Pamphlets: First Aid and Child Care, 1932-1938; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Pamphlets: Labor Organizations, 1930-1940; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Joseph and Helen Oken North Certificates, 1928, 1943-1944; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Joseph and Helen Oken North Wallets and Passports, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Helen Oken North Account Book, 1941 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Helen Oken North Autograph Book, 1925; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Helen Oken North Communist Party Membership Book, undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Helen Oken North Datebook, 1953; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Helen Oken North Diplomas, 1925, 1928 (Box MSOS 006)
    - Helen Oken North Engagement Calendar, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Helen Oken North Notebook and Telephone Numbers, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Helen Oken North Working Cards and Membership Booklets, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Nora North: Desk Diary, 1960; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Spanish Song Books, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 28)
- Series II: Morris and Jennie Oken Papers, 1920-1953; 1 box
  This series contains materials related Helen Oken North's parents Morris and Jennie Oken. This series consists of correspondence written to the Okens from friends and family as well as several materials related to union involvement.
  - Morris and Jennie Oken: Incoming Correspondence, 1920-1943; 4 folders (Box 8, Folder 29-32)
  - Morris and Jennie Oken: Incoming Correspondence, 1944-1953; 6 folders (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
  - Morris Oken: Correspondence Regarding Injury at New York Naval Yard, 1945-1946; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Mary Oken Wilson Correspondence, 1944-1953; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Morris Oken: International Workers Order Flyers and Pamphlets, 1946-1952; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Morris and Jennie Oken: Notes and Clippings, 1950s; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Morris Oken: Labor Organizations, 1920s-1950s; 2 folders (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
  - Morris and Jennie Oken: Labor Organizations, 1951-1953; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Morris Oken: Membership Cards and Membership Books, 1913-1946; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Morris and Jennie Oken: Notebooks and Billfolds, undated; 1 folder (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Series III: Lydia Oken Mates Papers, 1921-1975; 1 box
  This series contains the papers of Helen Oken North's sister Lydia Oken Mates and her husband Dave Mates. This series is comprised primarily of correspondence written to Lydia by her sisters and parents. Some correspondence is also addressed to Dave Mates. Also included in this series are union membership cards; materials related to Lydia's education including diplomas, a graduation program, and an autograph book; and other assorted ephemera.
  - Lydia Oken Mates: Incoming Correspondence, 1921-1965; 13 folders (Box 9, Folder 16-26, Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Dave and Lydia Oken Mates: Incoming Correspondence, 1959-1974; 5 folders (Box 10, Folder 3-7)
  - Lydia Oken Mates: collection of Letters of Daniel North to his mother Helen North, Aug. 1948-Dec.1948; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Lydia Oken Mates: Letters and Clippings related to the death of Alice Herz, Mar. 1965-May 1965; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Dave and Lydia Oken Mates: Materials related to Communism in China and Vietnam, 1974; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Dave Mates: Sales Reports, 1967; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Lydia Oken Mates: Diplomas and Certificates, 1923-1927 (Box MSOS 006)
  - Walton High School Graduation Program, Jan. 26, 1927; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Lydia Oken Mates: English Assignment "The Modern School of Stelton", May 3, 1927; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Lydia Oken Mates: Labor Union Membership Cards, 1929; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Lydia Oken Mates: Autograph Book, 1924-1927; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Dave and Lydia Oken Mates: "Museum of First Congress-CPC" Postcards, undated; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Memorial Materials: Harry and Esther North, Abe Soifer, 2002-2003; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Lydia Oken Mates: Sketches, undated; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Lydia Oken Mates: Brochures and Clippings related to art, undated; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Dave Mates Wallet, undated; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Cocolo by Bettina Elrich, Jan. 1, 1945; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - News of Peace, Oct. 1951-Mar. 1953; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 22)
- Series IV: Photographs, 1935-1972; 0.75 Linear Feet
  This series consists primarily photographs and negatives related to Joseph and Helen Oken North and Dave and Lydia Mates. Images related to Joseph and Helen North consist of prints and negatives that date from 1935-1937 and depict their son Daniel as a baby and other events with friends and family from those years. Images related to Dave and Lydia Mates date from the 1950s to the 1970s and document their various travels, including trips to China and Russia.
  - Spanish Civil War Scrapbook, 1937-1939; 1 box (Box 11)
  - Joseph and Helen North Family Photographs, 1935-1937; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Helen North: X-Ray, 1946; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Photograph: Nora North, Jan. 1951; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Photograph of Helen and Lydia Oken, undated; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Joseph and Helen North: Unidentified, undated; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - Morris and Jennie Oken: Photograph "Matutinal Ablutions", undated; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Lydia Oken Mates: "Snow", undated; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Lydia and Dave Mates Photographs- [China], 1950s; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 30)
  - Lydia and Dave Mates Photographs, Sep. 1972, Nov. 1972, undated; 4 folders (Box 10, Folder 31-34)
  - Lydia and Dave Mates Unidentified Negatives, undated; 1 folder (Box 14)